Impact Visuals Photograph Collection
© 2003 University of Connecticut
Impact Visuals Photograph Collection.
undated, 1964-2000 [bulk 1983-1999].
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Impact Visuals.
6.5 linear feet.
Photographs, slides and negatives primarily of South Africa and the anti-apartheid movement. Some supporting material on photo cooperatives and the shooting death of Abdul Shariff, one of the photographers represented in the collection.
MSS20030047
History
Impact Visuals was a New York City-based cooperative photo agency dedicated to social documentary photography. Founded by Michael Kaufman, Impact Visuals operated for 15 years until shutting down in 2001. Most of the images in this collection were obtained when Impact Visuals acquired defunct South African cooperative Afrapix's material. Afrapix was a collective, self-funded group of freelance photographers in South Africa operating between 1982-1992. A few additional images came from Southlight Photographic Agency.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of photographs, slides, and negatives, as well as a limited amount of supporting materials and publications. The vast majority of the material relates to South Africa. Other Africa n nations, Holland, Palestine, Yugoslovia, and even New Jersey in the USA are also pictured. South Africa's first interracial elections in April 1994 are particularly well represented in the collection, as are the African National Congress (ANC), Nelson Mandela and Winnie Mandela, and National Party President F.W. De Klerk. Subjects other than politics include the environment, labor, economics, health, poverty, and cultural life.
Abdul Shariff, one of the photographers who worked for Afrapix and later Impact Visuals, was killed while documenting an ANC event in January 1994. Shariff's curriculum vitae, contract with Impact Visuals, and correspondence with fellow photographer Ansell Horn document the working relationships of a South African photographer.
Arrangement
Supporting material is located first, then all photographs are separated by photographer. Photographs are arranged chronologically with only general subject listings. The collection is not processed to the item level. Individual photographs have been captioned by the photographer.
Organization
Series I: Supporting Material, undated and 1994.
Series II: Abdul Shariff, 1990-1994
Series III: Ansell Horn, 1973-1996
Series IV: Eric Miller, 1983-2000
Series V: Rodger Bosch, 1988-1999
Series VI: Other Photographers in Alphabetical Order, 1964-1995
Separated Material
Shaken Roots: The Bushmen of Namibia. Text by Megan Biesele. Photography by Paul Weinberg. EAD Publications: Marshalltown, South Africa, 1990. Dodd A4951
Related Material
The University of Connecticut has an ongoing cooperative relationship with the African National Congress and University of Fort Hare to document the history of the ANC. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Organizations:
Places:
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Photocopies.; Books.; Contracts.; Newspapers.; Color slides.
Occupations:
Photographer.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The material in this collection was purchased from the photographers after the dissolution of Impact Visuals in 2001.
Abbreviations
ANC = African National Congress
AWB = Afrikaner Resistance Movement
Cape = Cape Town
COSATU = Congress of South African Trade Unions
Jo'burg = Johannesburg
MK = Mkhonto weSizwe ("Spear of the Nation"--ANC's armed wing)
NP = National Party
PAC = Pan African Congress
PAGAD = People Against Gangsterism And Drugs
SADTU = South African Democratic Teachers Union
SAF = South Africa
SPLA = Sudanese Peoples Liberation Army
SWAPO = South West African People's Party
TEC = Transitional Executive Council
UN = United Nations
WTC = World Trade Center, NYC
Detailed Description
- Series I: Supporting Material, undated, 1964-1994
  - Impact Visuals annual reports and labor brochures, 1993-1996 (Box 1:1)
  - Southlight Photographic Agency, undated (Box 1:2)
  - Correspondence between Abdul Shariff and Ansell Horn, 1993 (Box 1:3)
  - Shariff's work for Impact Visuals, 1991-1994 (Box 1:4)
  - Impact Visuals publications on Shariff's death, 1994 (Box 1:5)
  - Newspaper clippings on Shariff's death,1994 (Box 1:6)
  - Photographs of Shariff by Rutgers and Ansell Horn, 1993-1994 (Box 1:7)
- Series II: Abdul Shariff, 1990-1994
  - Positives Color,1990-1993 (Box 1:8)
  - Negatives B&W and Contact Sheets, 1991 (Box 1:9)
  - Negatives B&W,1991-1993 (Box 1:10)
  - Negatives Color,undated, 1993 (Box 1:11)
  - Negatives Color and Contact Sheet, 1994 (Box 1:12)
  - Prints Color 8x10, 1994 (Box 1:13)
    - SAF Violence: Shariff's last roll of film
  - Prints Color Oversize,1992 (Box 1:14)
    - SAF Labor and Refugees
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1991 (Box 1:15)
    - Jan.-Jun.: SAF Political opposition & leadership
    - Jul.-Oct.: SAF Poverty, hostels, townships
    - Nov. 4: SAF Jo'burg, Labor: COSATU strike
    - Dec.: SAF Poverty: homeless, unemployment
    - Dec. 20: SAF Politics: 1st Codesa meeting-DeKlerk, Mandela
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1992 (Box 1:16)
    - Jan.-Feb.: SAF Violence, Labor: Inkatha
    - Mar. 21: SAF commemorate 1960 Sharpville massacre
    - Mar.-Apr.: SAF Labor, Violence, Refugees in hostels
    - May 15: SAF Codesa II: ANC and S.A. Gov't
    - Mar. 21: SAF commemorate 1960 Sharpville massacre
    - May-Jun.: SAF prostitutes, squatters
    - Jun. 18: SAF Boipatong: day after Inkatha massacre kills 39
    - Jul.-Dec.: SAF political demonstrations
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1993 (Box 1:17)
    - Jan.-Jun.: SAF Right wing protestors
    - Jul. 14: SAF Soweto, Jo'burg: voter education
    - Nov.: Mozambique, Refugees
    - Nov. 17: SAF Personalities at WTC endorse new constitution
  - Slides Color (Box 1:18)
  - Slides Color (Box 1:19)
  - Slides Color (Box 1:20)
- Series III: Ansell Horn,1973-1996
  - Prints Color 8x10,1994 (Box 1:21)
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1973-1988 (Box 1:22)
    - Jun.'73: SAF Soweto township children
    - Jun.'85-88:SAF Jo'burg white/black, Jewish; education, labor, economy
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1988-1991 (Box 1:23)
    - Apr.'89: SAF Education: University students strike, alternative schools
    - Dec.'91: SAF Jo'burg suburbs, Labor, Economy: black/white
    - Dec.'91: SAF Jo'burg New Nation Writer's Conference at Wits University with Nadine Gordimer (Nobel Prize)
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1992-1994 (Box 1:24)
    - '92-93: SAF Jo'burg suburbs, Economy: domestics, security
    - Mar.'93: SAF Jo'burg downtown, Education: black schools
    - Apr.'94: SAF Elections: Indian township rallies / SWAPO squatters
  - Prints B&W 8x10,Apr. 1994 (Box 1:25)
    - Apr. 22-25: SAF Elections: rallies, politicians, registering
    - Apr. 25: SAF Bhambayi (once Indian) squatter camp
  - Prints B&W 8x10,Apr.-May 1994 (Box 1:26)
    - Apr. 26-28: SAF Elections: ballots, voting
    - May 1-2: SAF Elections: celebrations
    - May: SAF Orange Farm squatters Economy: sewing, building, schools
  - Prints B&W 8x10,Jan. 1996 (Box 1:27)
    - Jan.: SAF Cape Government: Apartheid paintings to be removed
    - Jan. 16: SAF Soweto Health: hospital, med. students, AIDS
    - Jan. 17: SAF Venterspost clinic: 1 nurse to ~100 patients
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1996 (Box 1:28)
    - Jan. 17: SAF Gauteng Labor: building clinic for rural poor
    - Jan. 19: SAF Cape High School: formerly all-white
  - Slides Color (Box 1:29)
  - Slides Color (Box 1:30)
- Series IV: Eric Miller,1983-2000
  - Publications,undated, 2000 (Box 1:31)
  - Negatives Color,Apr. 1990 (Box 1:32)
    - SAF Persons: Pres. DeKlerk with Inkatha's Gatsha Buthelezi
  - Captions and Prints Color 5x7,Apr. 1993 (Box 1:33)
    - Apr. 12-14 SAF Cape, Funeral, Violence: riots after Chris Hani's murder
  - Prints Color 8x10,1992-1993 (Box 1:34)
    - Jan.-Feb.'92: SAF Cape, Politics: ANC "People's Parliament"
    - Mar.'92: SAF Cape, De Klerk whites only referendum campaign
    - Jul. 15: SAF Cape, Politics: ANC Mass Action Campaign
    - Aug. 3: SAF Cape, Nyanga township: ANC General Strike, day 1
    - Jun.'93: South Sudan, Kongor, Famine: children, UN relief supplies
    - Jul. 26,'93: SAF Cape, Violence: St. James Church attack survivors
  - Prints Color 6x9,undated, 1993 (Box 1:35)
    - undated: Rwanda UN soldiers in Kigali, Red Cross aid, SAF Farming
    - 1993: SAF Cape, Personalities: Winnie Mandela, Buthelezi
    - May 2-3: SAF East London, Violence: white response to armed blacks attack in bar that killed 5 white men
    - Jun.: South Sudan, Kongor, Famine & Violence: orphans, SPLA war
    - Jun. 9-12: SAF Cape, Elections: voter education
    - Jul. 26: SAF Cape, Violence: St. James Church after grenade explosion
    - Sep.: SAF/Namibia, Walvis Bay Harbour, Fishing: changing hands in '94
    - Dec.: SAF Cape: Gay pride march
    - Dec.: SAF Cape, Gov't: transition from all-white Parliament
  - Prints Color 6x9,1994-1998 (Box 1:36)
    - Apr.'94: SAF, Politics, Elections: ANC and Inkatha in township
    - Jul.'94: SAF & other African nations, Personalities
    - Oct.'96: SAF-Mozambique border militarized
    - May '96: Uganda Politics, Economy, Labor: security forces parade, pre-election rally, safe-sex posters
    - Sep.'98: SAF Cape, Nelson Mandela with Cuba's Fidel Castro
  - Prints Color 5x8,1992 (Box 2:37)
    - Jul. 1: SAF Cape, Demonstration / Violence: COSATU protest march
    - Jul. 25: SAF Cape, Demonstration
    - Aug. 4-5: SAF Cape: ANC Mass action campaign
    - Sep.: SAF Cape, Violence: memorial after 29 ANC marchers killed
  - Prints Color 5x8,Jan.-Oct. 1993 (Box 2:38)
    - Jan.: Namibia, Environment
    - Feb.: SAF Durban Beachfront
    - Mar.: SAF Natal Midlands, Inkatha: ANC impi rally for Nelson Mandela, funerals for children slain in bus attack
    - Mar. 19: SAF Cape, Demo: Muslims mark Jerusalem day
    - Apr. 12-14: SAF Guguletu township, Funeral: looting after Chris Hani's murder
    - Jun.: South Sudan, Health, War
    - Aug. 26: SAF Gugulethu township, day after murder of Amy Biehl
    - Sep. 4: SAF Gugulethu township, peace marchers after Amy's death
    - Oct.'93: SAF Stellenbosch, De Klerk at NP Cape congress
    - Oct. 10: SAF Gugulethu township, Amy's memorial service with family
    - Oct. 13: SAF University of the Western Cape event to honor Amy
  - Prints Color 5x8,Nov. 1993-Feb. 1994 (Box 2:39)
    - Nov.'93: SAF Cape, PAC supporters protest trials
    - Nov.'93: SAF Cape, Person: Wilhelm Verwoerd, grandson of "architect of apartheid," campaigns for ANC
    - Nov.'93: SAF Western Cape, Right-wing military training camp
    - Dec.'93: SAF Cape, Elections: TEC Chief negotiator, Roelf Meyer
    - Dec.'93: SAF Cape, F.W. De Klerk: returns from receiving Nobel peace prize with Nelson Mandela to election rally
    - Jan. 15,'94: Namibia, Environment: rhinos, transportation
    - Feb.'94: SAF Hillview, Southern Cape, Housing: planning squatting
    - Feb.'94: SAF Cape, Elections: Mandela and De Klerk campaigning
  - Prints Color 5x8,Mar.-Jun. 1994 (Box 2:40)
    - Mar.: SAF Kraaifontein, Cape, Right: Neo-Nazi leader TerreBlanche
    - Mar.: SAF Cape, Coeberg Training Center: new National Peacekeeping Force (NPKF) training
    - Mar. 30: SAF Durban, Bhambayi township, Violence: attack by Inkatha
    - Apr. 1: SAF Durban, Bhambayi township, Demo for peace
    - Apr. 2: SAF Natal, Funeral: Inkatha and ANC areas
    - Apr. 30: SAF near Durban, Refugees: Indian area community center
    - Jun.: Rwanda, Kigali, Violence: Red Cross hospital, young girl shot
  - Prints Color 5x8,Jul. 1994-Apr. 1997 (Box 2:41)
    - Jul./Sep.'94: SAF Personalities: government ministers
    - Jan.'95: SAF, Argentina, Tunisia, Personalities
    - Mar./Jul.'95: SAF Parliament
    - Nov.'95: SAF Cape: U.S. Vice Pres. Al Gore visits
    - 1996: SAF Cape, Guguletu Township: soccer clinic for kids
    - 1997: SAF Cape, Sports & tourism: Olympic bid for 2004
    - Mar.'97: SAF Cape, Hilary Clinton & Chelsea with Mandela in former prison
    - Apr.'97: SAF Free State Province, Native traditional Basotho village
    - Apr.'97: Zaire (Congo), Kisangani: Refugees, children, women
    - Apr. 20,'97: Zaire, Kasese refugee camp, Violence: Rwanda n Hutu refugees one day before camp sealed off and 50-60,000 "disappeared"
  - Prints B&W 8x10,undated, 1983-1988 (Box 2:42)
    - undated: SAF Rustenburg & Stellenbosch, Cape, Farmers
    - undated: SAF Bushman, Soldiers
    - Nov. 2,'83: SAF Elections: Right-wingers
    - Jul.'86: SAF Jo'burg, Military Parade SAF Defense Force 75th b-day
    - Aug.-Dec.'86: SAF Jo'burg, Protest: imprisonment of children
    - Feb.'87: SAF Jo'burg, Military draft: compulsory service for white male
    - Feb.-Aug.'87: SAF Labor: unions & strikes, protests
    - Jun. 12,'87:SAF Jo'burg, member of Black Sash (women's civil rights) pickets anniversary of State of Emergency
    - Jun. 25,'87: SAF Mozambican refugees
    - Jul. 16-18,'88: SAF Nelson Mendela's 70th birthday celebrated by those calling for the ANC leader's release from prison
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1989 (Box 2:43)
    - Feb. 3,'89: SAF opening of Parliament with newly elected F.w. De Klerk
    - Feb. 14: SAF Cape, Archbishop Desmond Tutu
    - Mar. 9,'89: SAF Cape Prisons, protesting non-trial
    - Apr. 12-13: Namibia, Oshikango, War: SWAPO vs. Untag soldiers
    - Oct. 1: SAF Transkei Sabota funeral
    - Oct. 10: SAF Personalities: ANC leaders released from prison
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1990-1991 (Box 2:44)
    - May 2-4,'90: SAF Cape, ANC negotiation with SAF gov't
    - Dec.'90: Palestine, Ramalah & Jerusalem, Violence: Israel i soldiers, Palestinian protest
    - Sep.'91: Yugoslavia, War: at the Hague in Holland
    - Nov.'91: Holland, racist graffiti and signs
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1992 (Box 2:45)
    - 1992: SAF farming
    - Jan. 24: SAF Cape, PAC protest Parliament
    - Mar.: SAF Cape, Khayelitsha township, Health: child at clinic
    - Mar.: Apr.-SAF Cape, Education
    - Apr. 11: SAF Cape, F.W. De Klerk visits "colored" township in his "first electioneering type foray outside usual white constituency"
    - Oct.: SAF Cape, Guguletu township: Women: Adult literacy class
    - Nov.: SAF Durban Township, Poverty: homeless youths
    - Dec.: SAF Cape, Health: Prof. Chris Barnard, 1st heart transplant '67
    - Dec.: SAF Cape, Gay/Lesbian: Miss Gay Cape competition
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1993 (Box 2:46)
    - 1993: SAF Whites, Political Demonstrations
    - May 17: SAF Grabouw, Western Cape, Farming: apples
    - Jun.: SAF Squatters camp
    - Oct.: SAF Women Demonstration, reclaiming streets
    - Dec.: SAF Gov't, first sitting of TEC
    - Dec.: SAF Elections, "People's Forum" ANC campaign
  - Prints B&W 8x10,1994 (Box 2:47)
    - Apr. 20,'94: SAF Elections, F.W. De Klerk campaign poster defaced
    - Apr. 22,'94: SAF Cape, Political speech with time constraints
    - Apr. 23,'94: SAF Cape, Elections: NP Rally
    - Apr. 26,'94: SAF Cape, Elections: voting for disabled
    - Apr. 27,'94: SAF Cape, Elections: voting in townships and squatters
    - 1995: SAF Gov't, Labor
    - Jan.'95: SAF Cape, Funeral for Joe Slovo
    - Mar. 19,'95: SAF Cape, Ruyterwacht: Whites protest against black school
  - Slides Color (Box 2:48)
  - Slides Color (Box 2:49)
  - Slides Color (Box 2:50)
  - Slides Color (Box 2:51)
  - Slides Color (Box 2:52)
  - Slides Color (Box 2:53)
  - Slides Color (Box 2:54)
  - Slides Color (Box 2:55)
  - Slides Color (Box 2:56)
- Series V: Rodger Bosch,1988-1999
  - Color Trannies,undated (Box 2:57)
    - SAF / Swaziland, Inkatha: Mangosutho Buthelezi
    - May '93: SAF Environment, Scenic
  - B&W Trannies w/ Captions--Portfolio,1990-1991 (Box 2:58)
  - Text & Computer prints, 1997-1998 (Box 2:59)
    - Aug.'97-Jul.'98: SAF Cultural, African ballet program "Dance for All"
  - Color 8x10,May 1996 (Box 2:60)
    - SAF Human Rights: Truth Finding commission
  - Color 5x7,1993-1994 (Box 3:61)
    - Jul. 26,'93: SAF Kenilworth, Cape, Violence: St. James Church day after massacre
    - Jan.'94: SAF Person: Mandela pledges "Never Again" for prison
    - Feb.'94: SAF Elections: NP rally with DeKlerk
  - Color 5x7,1994-1996 (Box 3:62)
    - Feb.'94: SAF Elections: NP rally with DeKlerk
    - Feb.'96: SAF Cape, Culture: Luciano Pavarotti
    - Apr.-May '96: SAF Cape, Human Rights: Truth and Reconciliation Commission, Archbishop Desimond Tutu
    - May 29,'96: SAF Cape, Elections: municiple
    - Sep. 28,'96: SAF Cape, Drugs: Muslim group PAGAD marches
  - Color 6x8,1997-1999 (Box 3:63)
    - Feb.-Mar.'97: SAF Poverty: homeless children, prostitutes
    - Apr.'97: SAF Cape, Person: Nelson Mandela & Hillary Clinton
    - Jun.'97: Zaire, leader of new Congo, Laurent Kabila
    - Jun.'97: SAF Cape, Person: new leader of NP, Marthinus Van Schalkwyk
    - Feb.-May '99: SAF Violence, Gangs, Drugs
    - Jun.'99: Libya leader Muhammar Gadaffi
    - Jun. 2,'99: SAF Elections
    - Jul.'99: SAF Cape, Parliament: new President, Thabo Mbelei
  - B&W 8x10 / 5x7,1988-1991 (Box 3:64)
    - Jun.'88: SAF Jo'burg, Alexandria township, Children
    - Aug.-Oct.'99: SAF Violence, Protests Inkatha
    - Dec.'90: SAF white Afrikaner commemoration of victory over Zulu
    - 1991: SAF Violence, Education, Person: Nelson Mandela
  - B&W 8x10,1993-1994 (Box 3:65)
    - Jan.: SAF Personalities
    - Mar. 10,'93: SAF, Protests: against NP, Israel
    - Apr. 14,'93: SAF Cape Memorial / Riots after Chris Hani's death
    - May 7,'93: SAF Teachers Union, SADTU
    - Jul.'93: SAF Election practice
    - Sep.'93: SAF Family
    - Jan. 15,'94: SAF Person: Winnie Mandela supporting ANC's armed wing (MK)
    - Apr.'94: SAF Elections
    - May-Dec.'94: SAF Persons in Parliament
  - B&W 8x10,1995-1998 (Box 3:66)
    - May-Jul.'95: SAF Protests: unions, "born again" Christians, children, Muslims, AWB
    - Feb.'96: SAF Cape Person: Stebe Tswete, Minister of Sport
    - Jul.'96: SAF Cape, Human Rights: Truth and Reconciliation Commission hearings
    - Aug. 10,'96: SAF Cape, Drugs: Muslim group PAGAD marches
    - Apr.'97: SAF Education: children
    - Nov.'97: SAF Mental Health: patients and workers protest closing hospital
    - 1998: SAF Cape Gugulethu township, Culture: African ballet project "Dance for All"
- Series VI: Other Photographers in Alphabetical Order,1964-1995
  - Misc. Photographers (1 print each),undated, 1985-1990 (Box 3:67)
  - Unknown Photographers B&W 8x10 Prints,undated, 1964-1989 (Box 3:68)
  - Unknown Photographers Slides Color (Box 3:69)
  - Unknown Negatives and Copy/Publication,undated, 1985-1992 (Box 3:70)
  - Auf der Heyde, Peter (Box 3)
  - Bannister, Andrew (Box 3)
  - Bernstein, Suzy (Box 3)
  - Bradlow, Adil (Box 3)
  - Bronstein, Paula (Box 3)
  - Day, Anna (Box 3)
  - de Vlieg, Gill (Box 3)
  - Eliason, Orde (Box 3)
  - Elmendorp, Ellen (Box 3)
  - Eloff, Brett (Box 3)
  - Gool, Benny (Box 3)
  - Grendon, Paul (Box 3)
  - Hartman, Dave (Box 3)
  - Hilton-Barber, Steven (Box 3)
  - Hutchins, Mike (Box 3)
  - Kralj, Sasa (Box 3)
  - Kramer, Sue (Box 3)
  - Lawson, Lesley (Box 3)
  - Ledochowski, Chris (Box 3)
  - Lemon, T.J. (Box 3)
  - Liebenberg, John (Box 3)
  - Magwaza, Pax (Box 3)
  - Mayet, Rafs (Box 3)
  - Meintjes, Roger (Box 3)
  - Mofokeng, Santu (Box 3)
  - Moodliar, Deseni (Box 3)
  - Nunn, Cedric (Box 3)
  - Parker, Warren (Box 3)
  - Patzer, Marek (Box 3)
  - Sholk, Justin (Box 3)
  - Smit, Sandy (Box 3)
  - Southlight Collective Land Essay (Box 3)
  - Storkend, Sally (Box 3)
  - Tillim, Guy (Box 4)
  - Uzi, Avigail (Box 4)
  - van Der Merwe, Chris (Box 4)
  - Velasco, Paul (Box 4)
  - von Lohuzen, Kadir (Box 4)
  - Weinberg, Paul (Box 4)
  - Williams, Graeme (Box 4)
  - Wulfsohn, Gisele (Box 4)
  - Zietminski, Anna (Box 4)
  - Unsorted Slides (Box 4)
  - Unsorted Slides (Box 4)
- Oversized Material
  - Eric Miller's Portfolio,undated (Box 5)
    - Caption Listing,undated
    - Prints Color 11x16, undated
      - SAF Agriculture: Picture Story in Afrikaner village
    - Prints B&W 11x16,1988-1989
      - SAF Anti-Apartheid Protest, Eviction
    - Magazine: Ilford (SAF) winning entry,1989
      - SAF Environ.: Picture Story "Saving the White Rhino"
    - Magazine (Tearsheet) spread,undated
      - SAF Swaziland, Culture: concert